قرية الفريرية، قرية سورية تتبع ناحية جنديرس في منطقة عفرين.
Al-Fririyyah is a Syrian village belonging to the Jindires
sub-district in the Afrin region.
وهي تقع في الطرف الشرقي لسهل جنديرس.
It is located on the eastern edge of the Jindires plain.
يحدها شمالاً قرية تل حمو، ومن ثم طريق عفرين - جنديرس.
It is bordered to the north by the village of Tal Hamou, and
then the Afrin-Jindires road.
أيضاً جنوباً قرية الجلمة المحاذية لمحافظة إدلب.
Also to the south is the village of Al-Jalameh, which is
adjacent to the Idlib governorate.
وشرقاً قرية كفرزيت، غرباً جنديرس.
And to the east is the village of Kafr Zeit, and to the west
is Jindires.
سنكون معكم في هذه الحلقة في جولة داخل قرية الفريرية،
تابعونا.
In this episode, we will take you on a tour inside the
village of Al-Fririyyah, stay with us.
الفريرية، قرية سورية في جبل الكرد، تتبع ناحية جنديرس في
منطقة عفرين، محافظة حلب.
Al-Fririyyah is a Syrian village in Mount Kurd, belonging to
the Jindires sub-district in the Afrin region, Aleppo
governorate.
وتقع شمال وادي نهر عفرين بكيلومترين، وشرق بلدة جنديرس بنحو
اثني عشر كيلومتراً.
It is located two kilometers north of the Afrin River
valley, and about twelve kilometers east of the town of
Jindires.
تبلغ مساحة القرية ألف هكتار، وهي ذات تربة لحقية خصبة، غنية
بالمياه الجوفية،
The village has an area of one thousand hectares, and
features fertile alluvial soil, rich in groundwater.
وتتعدد فيها الآبار الارتوازية.
And it has numerous artesian wells.
توجد فيها مساحات واسعة من أشجار الزيتون، والباقي يزرع
بالحبوب والخضروات والمزروعات الشتوية.
There are vast areas of olive trees, and the rest is planted
with grains, vegetables, and winter crops.
يبلغ عدد سكان الفريرية قرابة أربعمائة عائلة،
The population of Al-Fririyyah is nearly four hundred
families,
موزعين بين عائلات كردية من آل عمو، وعائلات عربية تنتمي إلى
عشيرة بني زيد،
distributed among Kurdish families from the Ammo clan, and
Arab families belonging to the Bani Zaid tribe,
قدمت إلى القرية من الريف الشرقي لحلب، فضلاً عن مئة عائلة من
النازحين من مناطق سورية مختلفة.
who came to the village from the eastern countryside of
Aleppo, in addition to a hundred families of displaced
people from various Syrian regions.
وتتميز القرية بتربية الثروة الحيوانية بشكل كبير، وخاصة
الأغنام والماعز والأبقار.
The village is also known for significant livestock
breeding, especially sheep, goats, and cows.
حيث تعتبر تربية الحيوانات المصدر الثاني للدخل بعد الزراعة.
Animal husbandry is considered the second source of income
after agriculture.
افتتحت أول مدرسة ابتدائية في القرية في خمسينيات القرن
الماضي،
The first primary school in the village was opened in the
1950s.
ويوجد فيها عدد قليل من المحلات التجارية، وخاصة البقاليات
والسمانة.
It has a small number of commercial shops, especially
groceries and convenience stores.
يعمل معظم سكان قرية الفريرية في الزراعة، وخاصة الزراعة
المروية كالحبوب والخضروات،
Most of the residents of Al-Fririyyah village work in
agriculture, especially irrigated agriculture such as grains
and vegetables.
وأيضاً في تربية الحيوانات كالأغنام والماعز، وبعض رؤوس
الأبقار الموجودة في القرية.
And also in breeding animals like sheep and goats, and some
heads of cattle present in the village.
وتنقسم المكونات الاجتماعية فيها إلى المكون الكردي، وهم من آل
عمو، ملاك الأرض الأصليين.
The social components there are divided into the Kurdish
component, who are from the Ammo clan, the original
landowners.
وأيضاً العرب من بني زيد، والذين جاؤوا إلى هذه القرية من فاح
في ريف حلب الشرقي،
And also the Arabs from Bani Zaid, who came to this village
from Fah in the eastern countryside of Aleppo.
ومن ثم استملكوا بعض الأراضي الزراعية أثناء عمليات الإصلاح
الزراعي التي جرت في سوريا في ستينيات القرن الماضي.
Then they acquired some agricultural lands during the
agrarian reform processes that took place in Syria in the
1960s.
سنكون معكم في هذه الفقرة في جولة داخل حارات قرية الفريرية،
لنتعرف على أوضاع الناس المعيشية، وطريقة معيشتهم، تابعونا.
In this segment, we will take a tour through the
neighborhoods of Al-Fririyyah village, to learn about the
living conditions of the people and their way of life. Stay
with us.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
May God give you health too.
شلونك؟
How are you?
الحمد لله.
Praise be to God.
نتعرف عليك؟
Can we get to know you?
أحمد موسى من الفريرية.
Ahmed Musa from Al-Fririyyah.
الله يعطيك العافية، هلق شو عم تساوي؟ هذا موسم قرنبيط؟
May God give you health. What are you doing now? Is this the
cauliflower season?
والله هذا موسم القرنبيط وشوفة عينك عم نتعذب فيه من الأرض
لبين ما بنجيبه لهون وبنعبيه بالأكياس، وناخده عفرين وأسعار ما
في.
Well, this is the cauliflower season, and as you can see, we
are struggling with it from the field until we bring it here
and pack it in bags. We take it to Afrin and there are no
good prices.
ليش أسعار ما في؟
Why are there no prices?
أسعار ما في لأن جمرك كثير عم ياخذوا من العالم.
There are no prices because they take a lot of customs fees
from people.
جمرك شو؟
Customs for what?
جمرك للزراعة، مثلاً ابن دارة عزة بده يجي لعفرين ياخذ بضاعة
على الطريق بده يحط نص حق ونص البضاعة جمرك، يقول لك أنا ما
بجي.
Customs on agriculture. For example, a guy from Darat Izza
wants to come to Afrin to buy goods. On the way, he has to
pay half the price or half the goods as customs, so he says,
"I won't come."
هلق أنا لون ما في جمرك بروح على دارة عزة بتنباع أغلى معي من
هون.
Now, if there were no customs, I would go to Darat Izza; it
would sell for more there than here.
بس على دارة عزة بدي ياخذوا عشر دولارات على السيارة جمرك
وأجارها بدي يروح إلها تكلفة.
But to go to Darat Izza, they would take ten dollars per car
as customs, plus transportation costs. It costs a lot.
شقد زارع أنت؟
How much did you plant?
زارع مساحة هكتار.
I planted an area of one hectare.
هكتار، شقد سعره هون وكيف إنتاجه؟
A hectare. What is its price here and how is its production?
إنتاجه كويس بس أسعار ما في.
Its production is good, but there are no prices.
ليش ما في؟ شقد الكيلو هلق؟
Why isn't there? How much is a kilo now?
هلق الكيلو بـ 40 ليرة، هلق متحسن بـ 40، من فترة 20 يوم 15
يوم، 25، بـ 20 ليرة كان الكيلو.
Now a kilo is 40 liras. It has improved now to 40. About 20
or 15 days ago, it was 25 or 20 liras per kilo.
هلق هذا مروي ولا بعل؟
Now, is this irrigated or rainfed?
هذا مروي.
This is irrigated.
شو زارعين شي تاني كمان؟
What else have you planted?
ما في هو والملفوف لسا الملفوف ما حشناه بالأرض.
Nothing else, just this and cabbage. We haven't harvested
the cabbage from the land yet.
هيدي المزروعات الشتوية اللي بقرية الفريرية؟
Are these the winter crops in the village of Al-Fririyyah?
الشتوية إيه، سبانخ السبانخ وخلص انتهى موسمه، وفيه الفجل كمان
انتهى، كمان ببلاش كان، الشنتاية تمسك حقها 300 ليرة، الشنتاية
عم تكلف حقها الفاضية 100 ليرة، أجارها 100، 200 عم تصفي 100.
The winter ones, yes. Spinach, the spinach season is already
over. There's also radish, which is also over. It was also
sold for nothing. A bag would sell for 300 liras. The empty
bag itself costs 100 liras, transportation is 100... that's
200, so you're left with 100.
هلق هذا بيتكم هاد؟
Is this your house here?
هاد بيتنا إيه.
Yes, this is our house.
عندكم كأنه أبقار، فيه أغنام شي؟
It looks like you have cows, do you have any sheep?
إيه عندنا إيه.
Yes, we do.
فيه عندكم أبقار وأغنام؟
You have cows and sheep?
وهون الأخوات هنن؟
Yes.
And the sisters here are... ?
هنن هدول كلهم أخواتي هدول.
These are all my sisters.
أخواتك يعني، عم يشتغلوا معك؟
Your sisters, I mean, are they working with you?
عم يشتغلوا معنا إيه.
Yes, they are working with us.
عايشين والحمد لله رحمة رب العالمين أحسن من كل شي.
Making a living?
We are making a living, and thank God, the mercy of the Lord
of the Worlds is better than anything.
الحمد لله، الله يعطيكم العافية والله يرزقكم يا رب.
Praise be to God. May God give you health and provide for
you.
على راسي أستاذ، مية سلامة، على راسي، حياك الله ومية أهلاً
وسهلاً أستاذ.
You are welcome, sir. A hundred greetings. You are welcome,
may God greet you, a hundred welcomes, sir.
شلونك؟
How are you?
والله الحمد لله.
Praise be to God.
شو عم تساوي؟
What are you making?
والله عم نساوي عشا.
Well, we're making dinner.
عم تساوي عشا؟ إيش هو العشا عندك؟
Making dinner? What's for dinner?
بطاطا، عم نقلي بطاطا.
Potatoes, we're frying potatoes.
الشباب عم يشتغلوا بالقرنبيط، هدول عمال عندكم؟
The guys are working with cauliflower. Are they your
workers?
لا أهلي هنن صهوري.
No, they are my family, my brothers-in-law.
لك مين العمال عم تحكي لي؟ هون رح تسوي لهم عشا؟
So who are the workers you mentioned? Are you making dinner
for them?
إيه أخواتنا وولاد عمنا، ما في حدا غريب.
Yes, our brothers and our cousins. There's no one from
outside.
هلق إنتي شايفك عم تقلي على الحطب، ليش باركة برا؟ ليش مو جوا؟
I see you are frying on firewood. Why are you sitting
outside? Why not inside?
وين بدي أبرك؟ ما في عنا محل، بيتنا صغير.
Where would I sit? We don't have space; our house is small.
ما في محل.
There is no space.
وشغلكم كله على الحطب؟
And is all your cooking on firewood?
كله شغلنا على الحطب.
All our work is on firewood.
الجرة بـ 8 آلاف و9 آلاف، نحن ما بنحسن نشتري.
A gas cylinder is 8,000 or 9,000. We can't afford to buy it.
ما في.
We don't have enough.
شلون حالتكم، أنتي متزوجة؟
How is your situation? Are you married?
متزوجة.
I am married.
شو عندك أولاد؟
What children do you have?
عندي ولد وست بنات.
I have one boy and six girls.
ما شاء الله الله يخليهم.
Mashallah, may God keep them.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
شو بيشتغل زوجك؟
What does your husband do?
والله لا شغلة ولا عملة ما في شغل.
By God, no job, no work. There is no work.
بس عندكم أرض.
But you have land.
ما في عندنا أرض.
We have no land.
ما في عنا لا أرض ولا شي.
Then?
We have neither land nor anything.
ما في.
We have none.
عند أبوه إيه فيه، بس نحن لحالنا ما في.
His father has, yes, but we on our own don't have any.
يلا الله يعينكم.
Well, may God help you.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعين الجميع، الله يعطيك العافية.
May God help everyone. May God give you health.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته، أهلاً وسهلاً بخير الحمد
لله، شلونك؟
And upon you be peace, God's mercy and blessings. Welcome. I
am well, thank God. How are you?
الحمد لله، نتعرف عليك؟
Thank God. Can we get to know you?
إبراهيم برهو من قرية الفريرية.
Ibrahim Barhou from Al-Fririyyah village.
أهلاً وسهلاً فيك، شو عملك؟
Welcome. What is your job?
أولاً كنت رئيس جمعية سابقاً.
Formerly, I was the head of a cooperative.
فلاحية نعم.
An agricultural cooperative.
Agricultural, yes.
كويس، احكي لي عن أراضي الضيعة؟
Great. Tell me about the village's lands.
أراضي الضيعة بنزرعها بالحنطة، أول كنا نزرع شوندر، هلق
الشوندر بطلنا نزرعه الشوندر.
We plant the village's lands with wheat. Previously, we used
to plant sugar beets, now we stopped planting sugar beets.
حنطة وشو كمان؟
Wheat and what else?
حنطة، وشعير، وعدس، وحمص، وفول.
Wheat, barley, lentils, chickpeas, and fava beans.
هيدي مزروعات شتوية، والصيف شو بيزرعوا؟
These are winter crops, and in the summer what do they
plant?
بالصيف بنزرع مثلاً فليفلة، بندورة، خضروات يعني.
In the summer, we plant, for example, peppers, tomatoes,
vegetables basically.
طيب شقد مساحة أراضي الضيعة كلها بما إنك رئيس جمعية سابق؟
Alright, what is the total area of the village's lands,
since you are a former cooperative head?
حوالي 1000 هكتار.
About 1000 hectares.
1000 هكتار، فيها شي مشجر بالزيتون؟
1000 hectares. Are any of them planted with olive trees?
فيها تقريباً يعني بيطلع 500 هكتار.
Yes, there are approximately, it comes out to 500 hectares.
500 هكتار زيتون.
500 hectares of olives.
ما شاء الله.
Mashallah.
هلق عموماً يعني الأراضي هون مروية ولا كيف؟
Now, generally speaking, are the lands here irrigated or
what?
يعني الأكثرية مروية.
I mean, the majority is irrigated.
الأكثرية مروية؟ من وين مروية؟
The majority is irrigated? Where does the irrigation come
from?
المروية حوالي يمكن 300 هكتار تقريباً هيك شي.
Irrigated is maybe around 300 hectares, something like that.
من وين مروية؟
Where is the irrigation from?
في مروية.
There are irrigated lands.
من وين هدول؟ يعني من نهر عفرين؟
Where from? I mean, from the Afrin River?
إيه من مية السد.
Yes, from the dam water.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك أهلاً وسهلاً فيك.
May God give you health. You are welcome here.
حياك الله، شكراً إلك.
God greet you, thank you.
أهلاً وسهلاً مية أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome, a hundred welcomes.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته، مية سلامة يا أستاذ.
And upon you be peace, God's mercy and blessings, a hundred
greetings, sir.
شلونك؟
How are you?
يا مية هلا.
A hundred welcomes.
نتعرف عليك.
Can we get to know you?
أنا جميل محمد ابن أحمد شيخ عشيرة بني زيد في قرية الفريرية.
I am Jamil Muhammad, son of Ahmed, sheikh of the Bani Zaid
tribe in Al-Fririyyah village.
حياك الله يا شيخ.
May God greet you, Sheikh.
من قال.
And you as well.
طالما أنت شيخ العشيرة معناها بتعرف أوضاع الناس هون، احكي لنا
عن أوضاع الناس هون؟
Since you are the sheikh of the tribe, that means you know
the situation of the people here. Tell us about the
situation of the people here.
أوضاع الناس، وضع بشكل عام تعبان يا أستاذ.
The situation of the people, the situation in general is
difficult, sir.
يعني ثلاثة أرباع العالم بدي أقول لك تعبان وضعه، وربع بيكون
ماشي حاله.
I mean, three-quarters of the people, I must tell you, their
situation is difficult, and a quarter are doing okay.
يعني حتى مربين الأغنام هلق بالشتاء ما في محل شبر تسرح مربين
الأغنام.
I mean, even the sheep breeders, now in the winter, there's
not an inch of space for sheep breeders to graze.
يعني الناس بتشتغل بالزراعة ورعي الأغنام.
So people work in agriculture and sheep herding.
ناس بالزراعة وناس مربين أغنام، يعني حتى مربي الأغنام هلق بده
يطالع الغنم ما بيحسن يطالع الغنم.
Some in agriculture and some are sheep breeders. I mean,
even the sheep breeder, if he wants to take the sheep out
now, he can't.
ما في أرض يعني، أرض بائرة ما في.
There is no land, I mean, there is no uncultivated land.
كلها أراضي زراعية.
It's all agricultural land.
طيب خليك معي شوي، شقد عدد سكان هالضيعة؟
Alright, stay with me for a moment. What is the population
of this village?
عدد سكان الضيعة حوالي الخمس آلاف نسمة وأكثر.
The population of the village is about five thousand people
and more.
من عدا اللاجئين.
Excluding the refugees?
النازحين.
Displaced people.
كم عيلة في عندكم من النازحين؟
How many displaced families do you have?
النازحين حوالي الـ 100 عيلة عندنا.
Displaced people, we have about 100 families.
من وين هنن؟
Where are they from?
حوالي من حوالي حماة ومن حوالي سراقب ومن حوالي المعرة.
Some from around Hama, some from around Saraqib, and from
around Al-Ma'arra.
إيش أوضاعهم هدول؟ شو وين عايشين كيف ساكنين؟
What are their conditions? Where do they live, how are they
living?
ناس ساكنين بخيم، مقسم ساكنين ببيوت، بيوت شعر.
Some live in tents, part of them live in houses, hair tents.
بيوت شعر ولا بيوت في الضيعة؟
Hair tents or houses in the village?
قسم بيوت شعر وقسم مساكن بالضيعة، قسم قليل.
Part of them in hair tents, and part of them in housing in
the village, a small part.
طيب اللي ساكنين مساكن بالضيعة، مستأجرين؟
Well, those living in housing in the village, are they
renting?
لا.
No.
مجلس القرية أعطاهم البيوت.
The village council gave them the houses.
مجاناً يعني.
For free, you mean.
مجلس القرية إيه.
The village council, yes.
في بيوت فاضية من الناس مثلاً رايحين أعطاهم، إيش بيشتغلوا
هدول الناس؟
There are empty houses from people who, for example, have
left. So they gave them to them. What do these people do for
work?
هدول ناس ما في، قسم عمال زراعيين يعني يشتغلوا عندي وعند
الثاني، وفي قسم مربين أغنام ما بيشتغلوا.
These people, there isn't... a portion are agricultural
workers, meaning they work for me and for others. And
there's a portion who are sheep breeders and don't work (in
farming).
ما بيشتغلوا.
They don't work.
إيه ما بيشتغلوا.
Yes, they don't work.
طيب اليوم إيش هو موسم الضيعة حالياً؟
Okay, today, what is the village's current season?
حالياً موسم الضيعة موسم شتوي، قرنبيط.
Currently, the village's season is the winter season:
cauliflower.
ملفوف اللي نحن بنقول له زهرة.
Cabbage, what we call cauliflower.
سبانخ، فجل، هذا موسم الضيعة، وموسم يعني كله ما بيطالع تعبه.
Spinach, radish. This is the village's season, and a season
that, honestly, doesn't even cover the effort put into it.
الفلاح بيركض وبيتعب وما بيطالع تعبه الفلاح.
The farmer runs around and gets tired, and the farmer
doesn't make up for his effort.
أنا شايف ورانا في بطاطا كمان.
I see there are potatoes behind us too.
وفي بطاطا عفواً، في بطاطا، البطاطا هدول كمان ناس مستأجرين
أراضي استئجار، يعني بيروح بيستأجر الأرض بـ 200، 300 ألف،
وبيحط البذار بـ 400 ألف.
And there are potatoes, excuse me. There are potatoes. As
for potatoes, these are people who rent land. I mean, they
go and rent the land for 200 or 300 thousand, and they put
in seeds for 400 thousand.
يعني بالآخر الموسم يا بيطلع مكسور يا بيرسمن.
I mean, at the end of the season, they either end up in debt
or just break even.
طيب المي مجانية هون، مروية ولا من النهر؟
Well, is the water free here? Is it irrigated or from the
river?
هو مو عم يزرع هون، عم يزرع بأراضي أجار بغير قرية، عم يستأجر
أجار.
He is not planting here. He is planting in rented lands in
another village. He is renting.
من حوالي 300 ألف الهكتار، وعم يصرف على الأجار، بيجيب طون
البطاطا بـ 400 ألف.
Around 300 thousand per hectare. And he spends on the rent.
He brings a ton of potatoes for 400 thousand.
شقد يومية العامل الزراعي؟
How much is the daily wage of an agricultural worker?
يومية العامل هون بـ 1000 ليرة، الساعة بـ 200 ليرة، 5 ساعات
بـ 1000 ليرة.
The daily wage for a worker here is 1000 liras. An hour is
200 liras. 5 hours is 1000 liras.
ربطة الخبز بـ 300 ليرة 800 غرام.
A bundle of bread is 300 liras for 800 grams.
طيب هذا الفلاح منين بيجيب؟
Well, where is this farmer supposed to get it from?
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك، مية أهلاً وسهلاً، وبنشكركم ونشكر تلفزيون حلب
اليوم، مية أهلاً وسهلاً فيكم.
May God grant you health too, a hundred welcomes. We thank
you, and we thank Halab Today TV. A hundred welcomes to you.
حياك الله.
May God greet you.
لا يمكن الحديث عن تاريخ ومراحل تاريخية لقرية الفريرية، فهذه
القرية كانت بالأصل مركزاً لإقامة آل عمو، العائلة الكردية
التي كانت تملك هذه القرية وبعض القرى المجاورة.
We cannot talk about the history and historical stages of
Al-Freriyah village, as this village was originally a
residence center for the Amo family, the Kurdish family that
owned this village and some of the neighboring villages.
السكان العرب الذين يسكنون هنا ينتسبون معظمهم إلى عشيرة بني
زيد، وقد جاءوا إلى هنا من قرية فاح في ريف حلب الشرقي، عندما
كانوا يتنقلون كرعاة للأغنام والماعز حول مجاري الأنهار.
Most of the Arab residents living here belong to the Bani
Zeid tribe, and they came here from the village of Fah in
the eastern countryside of Aleppo, when they were moving
around as sheep and goat herders around the riverbeds.
وقد استطاعوا الحصول على بعض الأراضي الزراعية بموجب عمليات
الإصلاح الزراعي التي جرت في ستينيات القرن الماضي.
They were able to acquire some agricultural land under the
agrarian reform operations that took place in the 1960s.
ومنذ ذلك التاريخ يمكن الحديث عن مجتمع في قرية الفريرية.
And since that date, we can talk about a community in the
village of Al-Freriyah.
سنكون معكم في هذه الفقرة في زيارة لبيت العم صبحي الحسين، أحد
الرجال الكبار في القرية، للحديث عن تاريخ هذه القرية وطبيعة
هذا المجتمع. تابعونا.
We will be with you in this segment on a visit to the house
of Uncle Subhi Al-Hussein, one of the elder men in the
village, to talk about the history of this village and the
nature of this community. Stay tuned.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
شلونك؟
How are you?
الحاج صبحي هون؟
Welcome, sir.
Is Haj Subhi here?
الحاج صبحي موجود، تفضل.
Haj Subhi is here, come in.
شرف.
Please.
يا رب.
Oh Lord.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله.
And peace and mercy of God be upon you.
حجي شلونك؟
Hajji, how are you?
مية هلا.
A hundred welcomes.
مية هلا، الحمد لله رب العالمين.
How is your health?
A hundred welcomes, praise be to God, Lord of the Worlds.
حياك الله. شرف ارتاح.
May God greet you. Please, have a seat.
شلونك؟ شلون صحتك؟
How are you? How is your health?
والله صحتي ما هي زيادة.
Well, my health is not that great.
سلامتك.
Get well soon.
الله يسلمك، معي شوية مرض، حاشاك.
May God keep you safe, I have some illness, pardon me.
سلامتك، قديش عمرك؟
Get well soon, how old are you?
عمري 87، دخلت بالـ 87.
I am 87, I entered my 87th year.
ما شاء الله، شب.
Ma sha'a Allah, a young man.
الحمد لله.
Praise be to God.
على هالهمة هي شب.
With this energy, you are a young man.
الحمد لله، الحمد لله.
Praise be to God, praise be to God.
والشب ابن ابنك؟
And the young man is your grandson?
ابن ابن أخوي.
The grandson of my brother.
نعم.
Your brother's grandson?
Yes.
الله يسلمك.
Welcome to you both.
May God keep you safe.
عمي تحكيلي شوي هيك إنتو ايمت جيتو على هالضيعة هي؟ إنتو من
الناس اللي إجو، من وين جيتو إنتو؟
Uncle, can you tell me a little about when you came to this
village? You are among the people who came here, where did
you come from?
إحنا كنا نتنقل من الجلمة على إسكّان على شاح الدير على
الغزاوية على الفريرية على أبو كعب على حجلر، بهالضياع هدول.
We used to move around from Al-Jalmah to Iskan, to Shah Al-
Deir, to Al-Ghazawiyah, to Al-Freriyah, to Abu Kaab, to
Hajlar, among these villages.
ليش تنقلتوا؟
Why did you move around?
كان عندنا جمال ما في عندنا شيء، ويوم الرجاد نروح نرجاد على
الجمال، تانحط المونة. يخلص الرجاد نبرك ما في شيء.
We had camels, we didn't have anything else, and on the days
of harvest transport, we used to transport on the camels, to
store provisions. Once the harvest transport was done, we
would sit down, there was nothing else to do.
ما كان عندكم غنم؟
You didn't have sheep?
لا، غنمات كانوا عندنا شيء 20 - 30 غنمة.
No, we had about 20 or 30 sheep.
أنا عم أحكي عن أهل هالضيعة.
I am talking about the people of this village.
إيه أنا من أهل الضيعة.
Yes, I am from the people of the village.
إنت من أهل الضيعة، قصدي كل أهل الضيعة ما كان عندهم غنم؟
You are from the people of the village, I mean, didn't all
the people of the village have sheep?
ما عندهم منايح يعني غنم شلعة كبيرة ما في.
They didn't have milking livestock, meaning large flocks of
sheep, there weren't any.
الأصل من وين إنتو؟
Where are you originally from?
الأصل من فاح.
Originally from Fah.
فاح وين؟
Where is Fah?
شرقي حلب.
East of Aleppo.
وايمت جيتو؟
And when did you come?
والله أبوي جاي، أنا ما جيت أنا، أنا خلقت هون، بس أبوي جاي من
مشرق.
Well, my father came, I didn't come, I was born here, but my
father came from the east.
هلق إنتو لأي عشيرة؟
Now, which tribe do you belong to?
بني زيد.
Bani Zeid.
كل الضيعة هون بني زيد؟
Is the whole village here Bani Zeid?
إيه العرب اللي فيها كلها بني زيد، بس في بيتين بوسبيع، وفي كم
بيت حضر، والباقي ثلاث أرباع بيوت أكراد، والباقي كنا بني زيد.
Yes, the Arabs in it are all Bani Zeid, but there are two
houses from Abu Sbei', and a few urban houses, and the rest,
three-quarters of the houses are Kurds, and the rest of us
were Bani Zeid.
بني زيد، ايمت جيتو إنتو بني زيد لهون؟
Bani Zeid, when did you, Bani Zeid, come here?
والله إحنا... أنا نفسي جينا بيتنا بالـ 62.
Well, we... I personally, our family came in '62.
62 جيتو على الضيعة؟
In '62 you came to the village?
كنا بالغزاوية.
We were in Al-Ghazawiyah.
لكن يعني كل بني زيد اللي إجوا لهون بأي... شقد صار لهم مثلاً؟
70؟ 80 سنة؟ 50 سنة؟
But I mean, all of Bani Zeid who came here, in which... how
long has it been for them, for example? 70? 80 years? 50
years?
لا، في منهم... هذا جده لأحمد الموسى، هذا مقيم هون، من الأصل
هون.
No, some of them... this grandfather of Ahmed Al-Mousa, he
has been residing here, he is originally from here.
من الأصل هون.
Originally from here.
والبقية؟
And the rest?
والبقية صاروا يتجمعوا على بعضهم يعني. كنا دايرين بهالضياع،
وصاروا يتجمعوا قرايبهم على بعضهم.
And the rest started gathering together. We were roaming
these villages, and their relatives started gathering
together.
لكن ما بتعرف من أي... من كم سنة؟
But you don't know from which... from how many years?
لا ما بعرف لا.
No, I don't know, no.
طيب احكيلي شلون كانت أول الفريرية وشلون هلق؟ عادات الناس
وتقاليدها وكيف كانوا عايشين؟
Well, tell me how Al-Freriyah was in the past and how it is
now? The customs and traditions of the people, and how were
they living?
أول كان الحكم للأغوات، وكانوا تحت الحكم عايشين، شو من قال
لهم الآغا ما بيخالفوه. مليحة، خربانة، ما بصير. مثل ما يقول.
In the past, the rule belonged to the Aghas, and they lived
under their rule. Whatever the Agha told them, they wouldn't
disobey. Whether it was good or bad, they couldn't. Just as
he says.
وهلق؟ شو كانوا يشتغلوا الناس؟
And now? What did people do for work?
كانوا فلاليح عند الأغوات، هذا يحصد وهذا يفلح وهذا لمن يحط
المونة ويبرك.
They were farmers for the Aghas, one would harvest, one
would plow, and one would store provisions and sit down.
ايمت صار عندهم أراضي؟
When did they get lands?
يوم من إجا الإصلاح بالـ 67. بالـ 67 توزع الأراضي للفلاليح،
أبو كتارين، وأبو ثلاثة، وأبو أربعة، يعني حسب العيلة. صار
عندهم شوية أرض، العالم صارت تعمر. أولي كان العمار كله
للأغوات، لأهل الملك، اللي يريدونه يبرك، واللي ما يريدونه
يطردونه برا.
When the reform came in '67. In '67, the lands were
distributed to the farmers, the one with two hectares,
three, or four, meaning according to the family size. They
got some land, and people started building. Before, all
buildings belonged to the Aghas, the owners of the property,
whoever they wanted could stay, and whoever they didn't
want, they would throw them out.
ايمت صارت الناس تمتهن يعني مهنة تربية الحيوانات؟ الغنم
والماعز والبقر؟
When did people start taking up the profession of animal
husbandry? Sheep, goats, and cows?
والله من جية الإصلاح يعني بعد ما إجا الإصلاح يعني، من الـ 67
يعني بس 70، 72 صارت الغنم، العالم صارت أراضي وبركت، قام
تحوي. هذا يحوي له غنمتين ثلاثة، يحوي له عشر عنزات، هذا.. أول
كان ما في.
Well, from the arrival of the reform, meaning after the
reform came, from '67, meaning just '70, '72 the sheep
started, people had lands and settled, and started
acquiring. This one gets two or three sheep, this one gets
ten goats... In the past, there was none.
طيب شلون كانت عاداتكم بالأفراح، بالأعراس، بالأحزان، كيف
كانت؟
Well, how were your customs in joys, in weddings, in
sorrows, how were they?
والله عادتنا بالأفراح، بالأعراس أولي كانت ما في منها.
Well, our customs in joys, in weddings, in the past were
unparalleled.
شلون؟ احكيلي.
How so? Tell me.
يساووا شرق الضيعة، يسهلوا الأرض، ويحطوا المنصات ويجي المطرب
يغني، والكهربا، وهالشي يعني، سيارات تجمع ما يعلم بيها غير
الله. بس لا من خمس ست سنين وجاي ما ظل، فرطت هالشغلة هي ما
ظلت.
They would prepare the eastern side of the village, level
the ground, set up the stages, and the singer would come to
sing, with electricity and all that. Cars would gather in
numbers known only to God. But no, for the past five or six
years, it hasn't remained, this thing fell apart and didn't
last.
إيش شو الدبكات والأغاني اللي تتغنى عندكم هون؟ إيش شو الدبكات
اللي هون؟
What are the Dabkes and songs that are sung here? What are
the Dabkes here?
دبكات عرب.
Arab Dabkes.
إيش شو هي، اسمها إيه؟
What are they, what are they called?
اسمها ولدة وقوصر، وشيخاني.
They are called Walda, Qawsar, and Sheikhani.
شيخاني لا، عندكم ما في شيخاني.
Sheikhani no, you don't have Sheikhani.
ولدة إيه.
Walda, yes.
في عندكم...
You have...
ولدة وشرقية و...
Walda and Sharqiyah and...
بتعرف إنت ترقص هدول عليهم؟
Do you know how to dance to these?
ها؟
Huh?
بتعرف ترقص عليهم؟
Do you know how to dance to them?
لكا! يوم من كنت شب أنا كنت أرقص.
Of course! When I was a young man, I used to dance.
ولساتك شب.
And you are still a young man.
لا هلق لا.
No, not now.
طيب. الغناء اللي هون، بدوي؟ عراقي؟ إيش شو؟
Alright. The singing here, is it Bedouin? Iraqi? What is it?
لا، بدوي. بدوي.
No, Bedouin. Bedouin.
يعني اللون لون بدوي؟
So the style is a Bedouin style?
إيه.
Yes.
طيب. احكيلي شلون اليوم الناس عايشين؟
Alright. Tell me how people are living today?
اليوم عايشين. لا ميتين من الجوع ولا شبعانين. معيشة عادية.
Today they are living. Neither dying of hunger nor full. A
normal living.
شلون يعني؟
How do you mean?
يعني اللي يحوي ربطة الخبز لولاده شبعانين، مبسوط هذا. في ناس
ما هي شبعانة الخبز.
Meaning whoever can afford a bundle of bread for his
children, they are full, he is happy. There are people who
are not full on bread.
حسبنا الله ونعم الوكيل.
God is sufficient for us, and He is the best disposer of
affairs.
إيه.
Yes.
لسه الناس متآلفة على بعضها؟ وشادة على بعضها؟ وفي هالتكافل
هاد اللي كنت عم تحكي عليه سابقاً بالأعراس وغيره؟
Are people still close to each other? Supporting each other?
And is there this solidarity you were talking about earlier
in weddings and such?
إيه إحنا هون البني زيد كليتنا، كليتنا شادين مع بعضنا،
عالحزن، وعلى الفرح، وعلى الكل.
Yes, we here, the Bani Zeid, all of us, all of us support
each other, in sorrow, in joy, and in everything.
ما شاء الله.
Ma sha'a Allah.
إيه.
Yes.
الله يقويكم يا رب.
May God give you strength, oh Lord.
آمين يا رب العالمين.
Amen, Lord of the Worlds.
الله يعطيك العافية يا عمو.
May God give you health, uncle.
الله يعافيك. أهلاً وسهلاً بكم، مية مرحبا.
May God grant you health. Welcome to you, a hundred
welcomes.
حياك الله.
May God greet you.
يا أهلين وسهلين، أهلاً، مع السلامات أهلاً.
A hundred welcomes, welcome, go in peace, welcome.
المصدر الثاني لدخل أهالي الفريرية هو تربية الحيوانات، وخاصة
الأغنام والماعز، حيث يوجد في هذه القرية حوالي 5000 رأس من
الأغنام والماعز، وما يزيد عن 100 رأس من الأبقار.
The second source of income for the people of Al-Freriyah is
animal husbandry, especially sheep and goats, as there are
about 5,000 heads of sheep and goats in this village, and
more than 100 heads of cows.
ربما انتشرت هذه المهنة، أقصد تربية المواشي، بسبب قرب القرية
من مجرى نهر عفرين، وأيضاً وجود بعض المراعي سابقاً. سنكون
معكم في هذه الفقرة لنتكلم عن واقع المواشي في قرية الفريرية.
تابعونا.
Perhaps this profession spread, I mean livestock breeding,
due to the village's proximity to the Afrin Riverbed, and
also the presence of some pastures previously. We will be
with you in this segment to talk about the reality of
livestock in the village of Al-Freriyah. Stay tuned.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
الله يعطيك العافية. شلونك؟ نتعرف عليك؟
May God give you health. How are you? Can we get to know
you?
عيسى محمد عيسى.
Issa Muhammad Issa.
الله يعطيك العافية، من أهالي الفريرية؟
May God give you health, from the people of Al-Freriyah?
أهلاً وسهلاً فيك.
Welcome to you.
هاد الغنم إلك؟
Are these sheep yours?
الحمد لله.
Praise be to God.
تحكي لي إيش قد في عندك كم راس؟
Can you tell me how many heads do you have?
عندي حوالي المية.
I have about a hundred.
ما شاء الله، الله يرزقك.
Ma sha'a Allah, may God bless you.
الله يسلمك يا رب.
May God keep you safe, oh Lord.
إيش شو واقع الأغنام هون في هالضيعة؟
What is the reality of the sheep here in this village?
واقع الأغنام ضيعة غنّامة. وفلاحين، مزارعين.
The reality of the sheep is that it's a sheep-raising
village. And farmers, agricultural workers.
نتعانى نحن، غنمنا هون. قلة مراعي. علف غالي.
We are suffering, our sheep are here. A lack of pastures.
Fodder is expensive.
في أمراض، اللقاحات ما عم نستفيد منها شي. عم يصير فيها أمراض،
عم يصير فيها نقص.
There are diseases, the vaccines are of no benefit to us.
They are getting diseases, there's a shortage in them.
نعم.
Yes.
أسعارها شلون اليوم؟ خلينا ندخل لجوا لهون.
How are their prices today? Let's go inside here.
أسعارها، يعني غنمة الكويسة بالـ 200.
Their prices, I mean a good sheep is for 200.
200 ألف؟
200 thousand?
200 ألف.
200 thousand.
هلق وشو أنواع الأغنام اللي عندكم؟
Now, what types of sheep do you have?
غنمنا عواس.
Our sheep are Awassi.
كله عواس؟
All of them Awassi?
كله عواس.
All of them Awassi.
هالضيعة كله عواس؟
The whole village is Awassi?
كله عواس.
All of them Awassi.
تقريباً كم راس غنم فيها؟
Approximately how many heads of sheep are there?
تقريباً 5000 راس.
Approximately 5,000 heads.
5000 راس؟
5,000 heads?
هلق هدول كلهن عواس؟
Yes.
Now, all of these are Awassi?
كله عواس.
All Awassi.
حالياً هذا الوقت هو وقت ولادة الأغنام؟
Currently, is this the time for the sheep to give birth?
ولادة الأغنام هلق هذا وقته.
Sheep birth, now is the time for it.
إيش قد صار ولد منهن مثلاً؟
How many of them have given birth, for example?
صار ولد منهن شيء حوالي 50 راس.
About 50 heads have given birth so far.
50 راس. إيش شو عم تطعموهن بهالفترة هيدي؟
50 heads. What are you feeding them during this period?
عم نطعميهن تبن. وشعير.
We are feeding them straw. And barley.
وقف هون لو سمحت.
Stand here, please.
تبن وشعير ونخالة.
Straw, barley, and bran.
تبن وشعير ونخالة؟
Straw, barley, and bran?
بس أنا شايف الدنيا يعني تقريباً صار ربيع.
But I see the weather, I mean it has almost become spring.
الدنيا ربيع بس ما عنا مجال. كلها أراضي زراعية، يعني ما في
مجال للأغنام تسرح تروح عا لچول كذا.
It is spring, but we have no space. It's all agricultural
land, meaning there is no space for the sheep to graze, to
go to the wilderness and so on.
يعني عم نطعميها من كيسنا.
Meaning we are feeding them out of our own pockets.
طيب على أطراف النهر؟
What about on the banks of the river?
على أطراف النهر للنهر مفلوح. أراضي زراعية.
On the banks of the river, up to the river it's plowed.
Agricultural lands.
ما في مراعي نهائياً؟
Are there absolutely no pastures?
ما في مراعي نهائياً.
There are absolutely no pastures.
ما عم تضمنوا أراضي؟
Aren't you renting lands?
هلق ما في وقت ضمان، توقيت شتوي.
Right now there is no renting time, it's wintertime.
طيب الحليب وين عم تروحوا فيه؟
Well, what are you doing with the milk?
الحليب حالياً ما في للربيع.
There is no milk currently until spring.
للشهر الثالث الربيع.
Until when?
Until the third month, the spring.
لكان الأغنام اللي ولدت إيش شو عم تسوي؟
Then what are the sheep that gave birth doing?
اللي ولدت يا دوب تشبع ولادها.
The ones that gave birth can barely satisfy their lambs.
تشبع ولادها.
Satisfy their lambs.
يا دوب تشبع ولادها.
They can barely satisfy their lambs.
يعني إيش قد اليوم مثلاً بيكلف تربية الخروف لحتى يعتمد على
نفسه؟
Meaning how much does it cost today, for example, to raise a
lamb until it can rely on itself?
يكلف حوالي من حدود على هاليوم بحدود الـ 20 من الـ 20 لـ 30
ألف.
It costs around, on this day, around 20, from 20 to 30
thousand.
20 لـ 30 ألف.
20 to 30 thousand.
احكيلي إيش شو في عندكم غير الغنم هون في الضيعة؟
Tell me, what do you have other than sheep here in the
village?
غنم نحن جماعة فلاحين غنم وزراعة.
Sheep, we are a group of farmers, sheep, and agriculture.
إيش شو غير الغنم من الحيوانات في؟
What other animals are there besides sheep?
في غنم في ماعز في بقر.
There are sheep, there are goats, there are cows.
إيش قد في ماعز وإيش قد في بقر؟
How many goats are there and how many cows are there?
في بحدود يعني والله احصائيا يعني بالضبط، بعرف الضيعة يعني
بحدود فيها بحدود الـ 5000 راس.
There are about, I mean by God, statistically speaking
exactly, I know the village, I mean it has about 5,000
heads.
5000 راس إيش شو؟
5,000 heads of what?
غنم، غنم عواس.
Sheep, Awassi sheep.
والماعز والبقر؟
And goats and cows?
الماعز...
Goats...
يعني بحدود الـ 500-600 راس.
Meaning around 500-600 heads.
والبقر؟
And the cows?
البقر بحدود الـ 100 راس.
The cows are around 100 heads.
الماعز اللي عندكم شو نوعه؟
What breed of goats do you have?
نوعه بلدي، نحن نسميه بلدي.
It's Baladi (local), we call it Baladi.
يعني شامي؟
Meaning Shami (Damascene)?
سوري بلدي.
Syrian Baladi.
هلق وين رابط الخراف الصغيرة؟
Now, where are the small sheep tied up?
رابطها هون، هذا محلها هون.
I tied them here, this is their place here.
نشوفهن؟
Shall we see them?
تفضل.
Please, go ahead.
هلق هون شايفهم كمان بين أمهاتهم؟
Now here, I see them with their mothers too?
هلق جينا تركناهم بين أمهاتهم.
We just came and left them with their mothers.
بالليل نحطهم هون بالصيرة.
At night we put them here in the pen.
يعني الخراف لحال والأمهات لحال؟ ليش؟
So the sheep are separated from their mothers? Why?
نفصلها صحية لأمهم، ومشان بالليل نعلفهم.
We separate them for their mothers' health, and so we can
feed them at night.
نعلف الخراف لحال، والأمهات لحال.
We feed the sheep separately, and the mothers separately.
وإذا نام مع أمه، بدعوس فوق منه وكذا بينزع له صوفه.
And if it sleeps with its mother, she might step on it and
ruin its wool.
هو الخروف؟
The sheep?
الخروف، ابنها.
The sheep, her baby.
هلق إذا عم تقلي العلف غالي، والدواء غالي.
Now, if you're telling me feed is expensive, and medicine is
expensive.
طيب، وكل شيء غالي، شقد سعر الحليب؟
Okay, and everything is expensive, how much is the price of
milk?
عم نجيب دواء ما عم نستفيد منه شيء.
We're buying medicine, but we're not benefiting from it at
all.
ليه؟
Why?
لقح فلان لقاح، ما عم نستفيد منه.
So-and-so vaccinates, but we aren't benefiting from it.
عم نجيب لقاحات وكذا ما عم نستفيد منها.
We're getting vaccines and such, but not benefiting from
them.
طيب، في شيء أمراض محددة عم تصيب الأغنام؟
Alright, are there specific diseases affecting the sheep?
إي.
Yes.
إيش هي مثل إيش؟
What are they, like what?
عندك حمة مصارين، عندك حمة المالطية.
You have enterotoxemia, you have Malta fever.
عندك الجدري، عندك اللي بيسموه طوبيق.
You have sheep pox, you have what they call "Toubeeq".
هذا كله بس بالفريرية ولا بالمنطقة؟
Is all this only in Al-Frayriyeh or in the region?
هذا بالمنطقة.
This is in the region.
بالمنطقة.
In the region.
طيب، شقد سعر كيلو الحليب اليوم؟ الغنم؟
Alright, how much is a kilo of milk today? Sheep's milk?
اليوم عم يقولوا يعني الحليب بالـ 250.
Today they say milk is at 250.
شو عم يقولوا إنت مو عم تبيع؟
What do you mean they say? Aren't you selling?
ما بعت لسع شيء.
I haven't sold anything yet.
بنبيع من الشهر الرابع ورا.
I see.
We sell from the fourth month onwards.
طيب واللبن؟
Okay, and yogurt?
اللبن عم يقولوا بحدود الـ 500.
They say yogurt is around 500.
500.
يعني هالحالة بتوفي معكم؟
So in this case, does it pay off for you?
بهالحالة عم نبيع منها لنطعميها.
In this case, we're selling some of them to feed the rest.
بتبيعوا من الغنم؟
Selling from the sheep?
نبيع منها هلق حالياً بالشتوية. بتوقيت الشتوي نبيع منها
لنطعميها.
We're selling some of them now in the wintertime. During
wintertime, we sell some of them to feed the rest.
عم نبيع منها لنطعميها، لنجيب لها علف.
We're selling from them to feed them, to buy feed for them.
شقد كان إنت القطيع تبعك؟
How big was your herd?
كان 170 راس.
It was 170 heads.
170 راس. ايمتى؟
170 heads. When?
بشهر الثامن.
In the eighth month.
وهلق؟
And now?
حوالي الـ 100.
Around 100.
100، ليش نقص؟
100, why did it decrease?
نقص 70 راس.
It decreased by 70 heads.
ليش؟
Why?
عم باكل منها وعم بطعمي ولادي وعم بطعميها.
I'm eating from them, feeding my kids, and feeding the herd.
معقول خلال سنة 70 راس؟
Is it possible that 70 heads were gone in a year?
معقولة.
It is possible.
لأني ما في، ما في مجال للمراعي.
Because there are no, there are no pastures available.
شايف هدول الـ... الماعز.
I see these... goats.
هدول شو نوعهم؟
What breed are these?
هدول نوعهم بلدي.
These are Baladi (local).
بلدي؟
Baladi?
خلينا نشوفهم شوي.
Baladi.
Let's take a look at them.
تفضل.
Please, go ahead.
احكيلي عنه هذا شو هذا؟
Tell me about this one, what is this?
هذا اسمه مرياع.
This is called a "Mirya'" (bellwether).
هذا مرياع؟
This is a Mirya'?
مرياع.
Mirya'.
هذا منه وصغير نشيله عن أمه ونربيه على الغنينة.
Since it was little, we took it from its mother and raised
it with a bottle.
نصير نرضعه على الغنينة.
We bottle-feed it.
نسميه مرياع، هذا ليهتم بالغنم ويلحق الراعي.
We call it a Mirya', this is to lead the sheep and follow
the shepherd.
الغنم ولا هذا ماعز؟ هذا مو غنم.
The sheep? But this is a goat! This isn't a sheep.
في ماعز وفي غنم.
There are goats and sheep.
عندي من الماعز وعندي من الغنم.
I have some goats and some sheep.
هذا شامي هو نفسه اللي بيقولوا له شامي؟
Is this Shami, the same one they call Shami?
هذا بلدي الأصلي.
This is original Baladi.
بلدي الأصلي، شو مواصفاته؟
Original Baladi, what are its features?
مواصفاته أبيض، أعجمي، هي مواصفاته.
Its features are white, A'jami (foreign lineage), these are
its features.
يعني جبهته، أنفه، أذنه...
You mean its forehead, nose, ear...
عادي، بلدي عادي.
Normal, normal Baladi.
إيش في غير البلدي من هالنوعية؟
What else is there besides Baladi of this kind?
في أحمر، في أسود، في من جميع الألوان.
There is red, there is black, there are all colors.
وفي غير بلدي؟
And are there any non-Baladi ones?
لا، عندنا هون غير بلدي ما عندنا أي شيء.
No, we don't have any non-Baladi ones here.
كل ماعز بلدي؟
Are all goats Baladi?
كله بلدي وولادة على إيدنا، يعني ما في شيء من برا.
All are Baladi and born in our hands, meaning there's
nothing from outside.
والغنم كله عواس؟
And all the sheep are Awassi?
كله عواس.
All are Awassi.
ما في غير نوعية؟
There's no other breed?
كله تربية على إيدنا.
We raised them all ourselves.
الله يعطيكم العافية ويطول بعمركم.
May God give you health and grant you a long life.
حبيب قلبي.
My beloved.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
حبيب قلبي.
My beloved.
انتهت حلقة هذا الأسبوع من برنامج "جولات".
This week's episode of the "Jawlat" (Tours) program has come
to an end.
والتي قدمناها لكم من قرية الفريرية التابعة لناحية جنديرس في
منطقة عفرين.
Which we presented to you from Al-Frayriyeh village, part of
the Jindires sub-district in the Afrin region.
سنكون معكم في الأسابيع القادمة في جولات جديدة من مناطق سورية
أخرى حبيبة.
We will be with you in the coming weeks on new tours from
other beloved Syrian regions.
لمتابعة برنامجنا تابعوا صفحة الفيس الخاصة بالقناة.
To follow our program, follow the channel's Facebook page.
وأيضاً موقعنا على الإنترنت Halabtodaytv.net.
And also our website Halabtodaytv.net.
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you.